如果你觉得人类第一次登月情节不够跌宕起伏的话
As if landing on the moon for the first time in human history wasn't dramatic enough
那来听听阿波罗11号遭遇的几次1202和一次1201程序报警的故事吧
Apollo 11 also experienced a series of 1202 program alarms and a 1201 program alarm;
一起了解一下
so here's what they mean.
想要知道这两个程序报警 我们要先稍微了解下阿波罗制导计算机（AGC）
To talk about these program alarms we have to dive into the Apollo guidance computer, just a little bit.
在阿波罗登月的年代 软件程序只够跑任务所需的内容
By the time the Apollo missions flew to the moon, the software program that ran the missions could fit,
而且是资源刚刚好够跑在一组只读磁芯存储器上
but only just fit, into a set of read-only magnetic cores.
这让计算机可以在任何时候读取跑一个程序时所需的内容
This meant that the pieces of information
the computer needed to run a mission could be called up at any time.
计算机还能在一个时间内同时运行多个程序 获得多个数据结果
The computer could also run a multiple programs simultaneously to get multiple data points at one time;
而这非常重要
which is really important.
我们以月球着陆的时候为例
Let's take, for example, the moment of landing on the moon.
计算机需要知道登月舱相对于月球表面的位置
The computer has to know where the lunar module is with reference to the lunar surface.
它还要知道姿态 速度 发动机工况
It also has to know its attitude, its speed, as well as engine performance.
这些数据是宇航员需要读取或者输入到计算机中然后读取DSKY上显示的
These are all data points that the astronauts needed to call up or input into the computer
and read off the DSKY.
如果你想了解更多DSKY的内容 与阿波罗制导计算机的“动词名词”操作原理
If you'd like to know a little bit more about the DSKY, and how the noun-verb situation worked on Apollo,
我以前做过一期视频讲这个
I do have a video about that right here.
我们回到阿波罗制导计算机在月球着陆的例子
So let's go back to the Apollo guidance computer and our example of landing on the moon.
我们知道在一个时刻会有很多不同的信息涌入计算机
We know that we need all these different pieces of information flowing into the computer at one time.
但阿波罗制导计算机是单核处理器系统
But the Apollo guidance computer was a single processor system,
它是怎么做到同时处理这些数据的？
so how could it actually manage all of these things simultaneously?
实际上它并不能
Well it actually couldn't.
它可以每次以极快的速度处理单独一个任务
It could process each one individually but extremely quickly.
处理器的高速加上人类很慢的反应时间
Take that fast processing power and mix it with slow human reaction time
就得到了看上去在并行运行的程序了
and you've got something that looks like it's running programs simultaneously;
虽然它们并不是同时运行的
even though they're not actually exactly simultaneous.
但这还有一个问题
But still there's a bit of a problem.
我们有这么多要处理的数据
We have all these different pieces of information that need to be processed
而且不能同时进行运算 那我们总要有个先后顺序
And we can't do them all at the same time; we have to put them in a priority order.
那你如何知道先跑哪个任务 然后挂起到哪里等待下次运行？
So how do you know which one to take first and where do they go when they queue up to be next in line?
阿波罗制导计算机有一组12字的存储空间 被称为核心集
The Apollo guidance computer had a 12 word data area called the core set.
这里会包含所有正在运行的程序
This contained all the information to execute a given program.
这样的核心集在指令舱上有六个 登月舱上有七个
There were six of these core sets in the command module and seven in the lunar module.
每个12字的核心集中的五个被处理中的信息所占用
In each 12 word core set: five words were taken up by processing information,
剩余的7个留作存储临时变量或在需要时提供额外存储
the seven remaining words were left for temporary variables or extra storage, whatever the need might be.
即5个字的内存用于执行程序
So five words of memory in the core set to execute a program
7个字的内容用于存储程序有关的变量和临时信息
and seven words for all the variables and temporary information associated with that program.
但事情开始变得复杂了
But it gets a little bit more complicated.
安排下一个运行的程序 大体流程如下
Scheduling the next program fell to the executive.
VAC: 全称是VECTOR ACCUMULATOR AREAS 矢量累加器存储区
类似于核心集存储区(Core set Area) VAC主要用于含矢量运算的程序中
首先查找程序的起始地址和优先级 然后把信息转交非矢量累加器流程
It looked at the task's starting address and its priority and then passed that information to a no vac routine
该流程会在核心集中查找程序执行的可用空间
This scanned the core sets to see where there was any available space for the program to execute
如果有的话 那存储位置在哪
and if so where that space was.
基本上就是在核心集中找空地 把程序扔进去跑
So basically it found an empty space in one of those core sets and put that program set to run in that space.
在穷举测试中 设计软件的MIT仪器实验室
Through exhaustive testing, teams at MIT's instrumentation lab that developed the software
找到了一种保证核心集不会被完全填满的方法
came up with a way such that no core set would ever be completely filled;
从而让下一个程序总能有空间运行
there would always be a space for the next task.
而且还考虑到了特殊情况
And of course there was also the variable
当要运行的程序优先级比正在运行的程序优先级高时
that if the task that needed to be done had a higher priority than one running
计算机可以中断当前程序 运行新的程序 过后再从中断点继续运行
it could be interrupted to run the new program and then pick back up where they left off.
所以程序设计上讲是不会超载运行的
So the program was never designed to be overloaded.
在任务重的任何时候都有足够的核心集像并行一般运行所需程序
There were enough core sets such that everything that would have to happen during a mission at any given time
could be run nearly simultaneously
或者在有可用空间时按计划运行
or else scheduled to run as soon as there was free space.
那阿波罗11号的程序报警是哪来的？
So where do the program alarms from the Apollo 11 mission come in?
看上去MIT的工程师设计了不会超载的系统
Well it seemed that the engineers at MIT thought they had developed a system that could not be overloaded.
但阿波罗11号的计算机的确超载了
But on Apollo 11 the computer did get overloaded.
在他们准备着陆月球的时候
In preparation for their lunar landing,
Command Service Module: CSM 指令舱+服务舱
尼尔·阿姆斯特朗和巴兹·奥尔德林打开了会和雷达以追踪指令-服务舱
Neil Armstrong and Buzz Aldrin turned on their rendezvous radar to track the command service module.
这是一种安全措施
This was a safety measure.
可以在登月舱中执行中止的时候追踪到CSM的位置
It tracked the CSM so it knew where it was in case they needed to do an abort in the lunar module.
两人把雷达调整至SLEW模式 意思是只能由宇航员手动控制指向
The crew left the radar on in slew mode meaning it had to be manually positioned by an astronaut
同时它也不会向计算机发送数据
and this also meant that it wasn't sending data to the computer.
但几位宇航员和任务控制中心的人们都不知道的是
But what neither the astronauts nor the guys in Mission Control knew was that
雷达耦合数据单元当时在向阿波罗制导计算机发送大量计数器中断信号
radar coupling data units were flooding the Apollo guidance computer with counter interrupt signals.
原因是计算机电源结构设计的疏忽
This was due to an oversight in the computer's power supply design structure.
这些信号占用了计算机处理时间的一小部分
These signals were taking up just a little bit of the computer's processing time
导致后台在持续运行这些错误的程序
and the spurious job kept running in the background.
而大家都不知道的是 这个信号会让登月相关的重要程序无法执行
So unbeknownst to anyone, this signal prevented vital programs associated with the landing from completing.
所以新来的程序送到计算机 发现没有地方执行
So when a new task was sent to the computer, there was nowhere for it to go.
正在运行和准备运行的程序占满了核心集和矢量累加存储区
The running and scheduled jobs were holding their core set and their vac areas.
新程序没地方跑
There was no clear space for a new job to be scheduled.
当计算机发现没有空间跑新程序的时候
When the executive found there was no place to put new programs
就触发了1201报警：执行溢出 - 无核心集
it triggered the 1201 alarm signaling: executive overflow - no core sets,
以及1202报警：执行溢出 - 无矢量累加存储区
and also the 1202 alarm signalling: executive overflow - no vac areas.
并在之后触发了软件重启
This in turn triggered a software reboot.
所有程序无论优先级 全部取消运行 并按顺序重新运行
All the jobs were cancelled regardless of priority and started up again as per their table order;
非常幸运的是 这个过程非常快 不会丢失制导和导航数据
so quickly that no guidance or navigational data was lost. Which is lucky!
阿波罗11号一共发生四次1202报警和一次1201报警
Apollo 11 had multiple of these alarms; four 1202 alarms and one 1201 alarm.
最终巴兹·奥尔德林察觉到了他想运行的程序和1202报警的关联
Eventually Buzz Aldrin realized there was a correlation
between one of the programs he was trying to run and the 1202 alarms.
每次他想运行程序以获得与着陆区的区域数据的时候 就会收到程序报警
Every time he tried to run the program that would call up range data to the landing area, he got that alarm.
所以他直接不用计算机运行这个程序了 而是管休斯敦要这个数据
So he stopped running it and asked Houston for the data instead.
当然 MIT的工程师也知道1201和1202报警不会有危险
Of course engineers from MIT knew the 1201 and 1202 program alarms were innocuous,
尤其对于阿波罗11号来说 显然这个程序报警没有触发中止着陆
especially in the case of Apollo 11, and as we know the alarms have not forced an abort.
尼尔·阿姆斯特朗和巴兹·奥尔德林在收到第一个1202报警不到十分钟后
Neil Armstrong and Buzz Aldrin were able to land the Eagle on the Sea Of Tranquility
就将鹰号登月舱着陆在月球的静海
less than 10 minutes after that first 1202 program alarm.
我在我的Discover博客上有很多关于计算机 核心集 矢量累加存储区的内容
I've got a more detailed look at how the computer works with the core sets and the vac areas,
还有很多阿波罗11号的故事
as well as a story of Apollo 11 over on my companion blog at discover.
所以我强烈推荐大家去看看 地址在视频详情
So I urge you guys to go check that out, the link is in the description
希望能解决大家的疑问
and hopefully will answer any lingering questions you might have.